So now let's do another example of list induction, of proving things with induction lists,
structural induction lists. So suppose, remember the function maximum, so I will rewrite it here again,
so maxlist, so it just returns the maximum element in the list recursively, so maximum of zero,
but maximum empty was that, and the maximum of a non-empty list was that, if you recall,
this function gives you the maximum of two natural numbers, so maxlist, so let me just
properly size that, so it is a recursive function, so a bit better, so consider a function, this function,
prove that, before we prove anything else, consider another function, also consider
the function listset or setlist, so this function returns the set of elements in the list, so
we'll just denote with that empty set, and the set of an empty list is insertion of x in list set of x's,
so here, note that insert, the function insert adds an element given list, okay,
now we want to prove the following, we want to prove that, if x is in list set of x's,
then we have that x is smaller than or equal maxlist of x's, okay, so that's a slightly different proof,
because here we have an assumption that implies something, so that means that we're going to have
a lot of forward reasoning, plus the step case will be a bit trickier than usual, because we'll have
more than just a lot of other assumptions, so the proof is by induction on x's, okay,
so remember we had that notation for the induction principle on lists, so if you have to prove any
property for any list x's, then you have to prove that property for the empty list,
you have to prove that property for in that way, you have to prove sure that if you have the
property holding for a list y's, then it also holds for that y's ending with any element y, okay,
so here, what is the property that we have? The property is this and that, so the property is
basically the x is in list x's implies that x is smaller than or equal maxlist, it's not just
that, what we want to prove is the whole thing, so the base case, we show that, so let me just
write a note here, so note the property is both the assumption, is not both, I would just say is
rather that is that the assumption implies the conclusion, not just the conclusion,
not just the conclusion, okay, a side note, we have two cases as usual in the base case,
so what is the base case? This time the base case without assumptions, so the assumption is
the premises are the following, that x is in this set of empty and the goal is
that x is smaller than or equal maxlist empty, okay, so the proof is simple, because
we firstly know that maxlist empty is going to be zero, okay, but there's no way, there's nothing,
we don't know anything about x, so we don't know whether x is actually zero, no, because the only
case in which x is more than or equal to zero is that x itself is zero, so we can't approach a proof
like that only, so let me just write that, so this should be by maxlist simps, in particular
this is as far as from that equation, the first equation that defines maxlist, okay, so
however, we know one thing that can help us through this, which is that x is in
list set empty, what does that mean? What that means is the following, so two,
like step number two doesn't have to do step number one from, we know that x is in the empty set,
okay, that's from the assumption, the base case assumption, but also another lemma,
which we don't have, which we need to find still, but that lemma basically says that
nothing can be in the empty list, right, so from base case assumption and, sorry, no, no,
from base case assumption, that's still, this lemma is used in next step, so from base case
assumption, so from the base case assumption we know that x is in the list set of empty list,
which means x is in the empty list, so base case assumption and substitution list set of empty,
sorry, list set simps, so now from this lemma number one, that nothing is in the empty set,
we can conclude that, we can basically conclude that a contradiction falls, so because we know
that nothing is in the empty set and we know that x is in the empty set here, then if something and
its own opposite are true, then we have a contradiction and we can then prove that,
we can basically prove anything from a contradiction by another law that says
false implies any property, so then we have, we can then just simply say that
x is smaller than equal max list empty set that's using lemma two and forward reasoning
with step number three and then here actually step number three, I didn't say what it falls from,
what it falls from, this follows from step number two and lemma one, maybe I'll just write lemma
three as well, lemma three says that if you have p and you have not p, the negation of p,
then you can get a false, okay, so that's for that, let me just write this with the usual notation,
our usual notation, so if you have p and not p, then you can get false, okay, so that's
then using step number two, lemma one and lemma three, where lemma three is, let me just write it
more precisely, so lemma three is instantiated with, assumptions of lemma three are instantiated with
two, step number two and lemma one, so that's forward reasoning, then we have the step case,
okay, and then the step case, let's go back to the theorem statement to just see what the
step case is going to be about, the step case is going to be about,
or even let's go back one slide, one page, so here the step case is the following,
if you have the property for y's, then you have the property holding for y's and then you can show
that the property holds for y's with any other element cons to the front of that y's, okay,
so here the property is that implication, right, so basically what we, the induction hypothesis will
be that implication, so an induction hypothesis will be just the implication for y's and or some x's,
if it doesn't matter the name, and the go and end, let me just show you, so what are we assuming the
assumptions? Firstly, the first assumption is the induction hypothesis, okay, what is induction
hypothesis is that x is in list set of y's, okay, implies that x is more than equal max list of y's,
the goal again is the property but applies to any y, a constant with the given y's, so the goal
basically is x is in list set y and y's implies x more than equal max list y and y's, let me just
move that a bit, so let's here y's and y's, okay, so as you can see here, the goal is actually has
something, implies something else, so what we can do is the following, you can, instead of doing that,
we can move, we can move that assumption, that assumption of the goal just with the other
assumptions, can make our lives easier, okay, so I'll just move that, so instead of this,
I'll just delete it like that instead, delete this, so the assumptions, the first assumption
is induction hypothesis and the second assumption, I'll just call it the premise, is that, okay,
so these are the assumptions, so premise, we only have one premise and the goal is that,
so what we did, all what I did is just moving, like splitting the property because it has an
assumption and a conclusion, the assumption going to the assumptions and the conclusion going to the
goal, okay, so now we can again proceed with our proof, so let's try that, so how do we prove that,
actually, we have, we can prove that, okay, we can prove that by case distinction,
so we either have that x is, have that x, yeah, one second, yeah, so we can just prove our lemma by
case splitting, okay, so we have that either x is the same as y, okay, because we have, we assume that x
is in the list set of y comes y, by definition of this set, we must have a lemma that says that x
will be equal to y or x is in this set of y's, so let's do the following then, firstly,
like do the proof by cases, so proof by cases on x equals y, right, so case one, x equals y,
so the first step will be the following, so if x equals y, that means that, that means that
we want to prove that basically y is smaller than max list y comes y's, right, because we
instantiated this, like we would then substitute y with x given the case assumption, so we want
to prove that, so how can we show that, so we must have a lemma about max, so we must have a lemma
that says that x, so lemma, I don't remember the number, I'll just say 1 for now, so lemma 1 here
should say that x is less than or equal to max list of x comes x's, or let me just change the
symbols so that's clear, I'm talking about arbitrary symbols there, so a is less than or equal to max
list of a comes a's, okay, so that should follow then, so that's in this, what we want here is that
it should follow from lemma 1, and then 2, we have x is smaller than max list y,
as y's, by substituting this assumption, right, this case assumption, okay, it's case 2,
so that does it for this one, it's a case 2, x is not equal to y, so how does that proof go?
The proof is different, so if x is not equal to y, remember I said, I said we need the dilemma about
the fact that if x is in list set y and y's, y comes y's, then we have that x is going to be other
equal to y or in y's, so let me just say that, if a is in list set b and b's, let's say
that implies that either a equal b or a is in list set of b's, right, so that's the
that's the same lemma, so from that we have that x is in list set y's, where do we have that from?
Case assumption and lemma 2, okay, I'm not really going through the low level reasoning,
as in I'm not saying whether that's forward or backward reasoning, because we need,
like in order for us to really properly do this lemma at the lowest level of detail,
and we need to come up with lemmas about this junction, I won't do that, but because it's clear,
so now, okay, we know that x is in list set of y's, this is the other case, then from that we
can apply the induction hypothesis, we know that x is, we know that because x is in list set of y's,
we can just use the induction hypothesis to get that by forward reasoning, so let's do that,
so from that we know that x is smaller than or equal max list of y's, that's from the induction
hypothesis with its assumption, essentially with one, right, so that that's forward reasoning,
that's a regular forward reasoning step, okay, now we still need to show that x is less than
max list of y times y's, remember that's our goal, so how can we show that? We need another lemma
that says, so what would this lemma be called, so let's just call this lemma 3 then,
so that lemma would say max list of a's smaller than max list of a comes a's, okay, so from that
so from that lemma we can conclude that x is smaller than equal max list, sorry not x,
we know we can, from that lemma we can conclude that max list of y's is smaller than max list y
comes y's, that's using lemma 3, then the last step will depends on, will depend on a
simple property which is transitivity of smaller than or equal, so if a is smaller than or equal to b
and b smaller than or equal to c then we know that a is more than or equal to c,
so if we apply lemma 4, so we can get x is smaller than less than max list,
give a bit of space there, max list of y comes y's, how? Using lemma 4 of 2 and 3,
forward reasoning and that basically is our goal, so that finishes our proof
and that's all for this induction, so please try to do these two proofs on your own,
just two proofs on your own and then let's discuss them in the large group tutorial.